Markus Lang

+852.91791091

mtvlang@protonmail.com

Diplom-Informatiker

Markus is a senior digital change and delivery professional with strong technological expertise, acting as business analyst, product owner or scrum master, with a consistent history of quick learning and high quality delivery in complex, global IT environments. Enthusiastic, with attention to detail while also ensuring that a clear, data driven and commercially viable approach and solution is delivered. Successfully led and completed re platforming and migration of online banking service for Barclays' Private Banking customer base as product owner/ lead business analyst in 2016.

Key Skills and Experience

10+ years experience of working in globally distributed projects with development teams and business stakeholders across multiple regions, languages and cultures.

Experience in data driven delivery of agile and waterfall/SDLC projects, acting as a Business Analyst, Product Owner or Scrum Master

Key area of expertise of implementing Digital Transformation and Regulatory Change projects in the context of Digital Banking for Private Banking/ Wealth Management and Retail Banking (Individuals and small Corporates).

SAFe Scrum Master (PSM I), HKU Introduction to FinTech, HKU Blockchain and FinTech, HKU FinTech Ethics and Risks

Familiar with Jira, Confluence, Sparx Enterprise Architect, SQL, Bash, GIT, (Python)

Fully bilingual in English and German (German national)

Career History

Parenting Expert/ Lead/ Coding for kids

8/2016 ongoing

Using a career hiatus to raise twins who will now be attending secondary school, allowing me to refocus on my career.

Skills gained include resilience to working under intense pressure as well as efficiency in managing tasks within constantly changing and unforgiving timelines requiring highly adaptable negotiation skills.

- Organised and taught multiple groups of kids coding online (Scratch)
- Various class teacher roles, assistant football coach
- Lunchbox preparation expert
- Designed and built embedded device for children time management education.
- Completed refresher courses in SAFe Scrum Master and HKU FinTech online training
- Completed online SQL training.

Lead Business Analyst/ Product Owner

1/2015 to 12/2015 4/2016 to 8/2016

Barclays Wealth and Investment Management UK

3+ years project to re-platform online banking offering for Wealth clients (Private Bank and International). Acting as the lead business analyst/ product owner for the Private Bank segment covering definition and validation of 1000+ requirements representing the digital banking proposition. Delivery responsibility for design and implementation of the target operational model which included support functions, fraud operations and client servicing, MI and associated workflow systems using a data driven approach to prioritize deliverables.

E2E design and implementation of Private Bank specific authentication, authorisation and credential provisioning including associated service functionality.

Project Management of regulatory change and FX projects on the target platform

Lead Business Analyst, HSBC Bank Plc

07/2014 to 01/2015

Global Standards, Global Banking and Markets, UK

3+ years project by Global Banking and Markets to develop and deploy Global Standards' policy – implementing a global KYC solution and operations for Global Banking and Markets' clients.

Key responsibilities included implementing and running a prioritised requirements backlog and supporting regional projects teams to align global and regional requirements.

Senior Business Analyst, Barclays Bank Plc

11/2013 to 04/2014

Global PMO Retail Bank, UK

As part of reviewing the waterfall approach to large scale change projects a review of the end to end change process was undertaken. Key responsibilities where to review the existing methodology and delivery of a RACI matrix covering all phases of large scale change projects.

Solution Business Analyst/ Project Manager

12/2012 to 07/2013

Barclays Wealth and Investment Management, UK

Working with business and operations to impact assess changes and dependencies for Wealth' online banking platform responsible for the E2E delivery of the product backlog for individual, corporate and intermediary clients:

- Changes to the multi-jurisdiction online payment functionality focussing on currency conversion
- Payment Service Directive regulatory changes

Barclays Wealth and Investment Management, UK

• Introduction of secure messaging for corporate and intermediary clients

Solution Architect

09/2010 to 11/2012

Moving from a shared services model Barclays Wealth Private Bank developed and deployed a dedicated system to support multi-jurisdictional business as part of project Gamma. This entailed working closely with business stakeholders, compliance, information security, operations and architecture to define an end-to-end solution for a new banking portal in a multi-platform SOA based environment. Included working closely with Barclays Capital and determining re-use of an award winning investment bank eCommerce platform. Key responsibility was the design, delivery and implementation of a multiplatform authentication and authorisation solution including associated provisioning and servicing functionality based on a SOA architecture and associated APIs.

Business Analyst 05/2007 to 08/2010

Barclays Bank Plc, Retail Digital Banking, UK

SCV (Single Customer View). Integration of customer product holdings into a single view to allow staff members in branch and telephony to view a customers full list of accounts and products. Responsible for business analysis and user acceptance testing.

Responsible for delivering a redefined customer authentication functionality for Barclays retail online banking with a focus on simplifying authentication and access levels in a two factor authentication context.

Acting as the Srum Master for the redesign of the online banking frontend (UX/UI)

Selected clients and projects:

airtelekom/ aceus, Bonn, Germany. Development of business concept for wireless ISP, Development of customer acquisition process, Specification for customer relation management system

Forming AG, Switzerland and Vinoform AG, Switzerland. Project management relaunch Corporate Identity

Alto Aviation Services GmbH, Berlin, Wiesbaden, Germany. Design, technical concept & specification, development and project management of a small aircraft identification system and strategy consulting

Bayer AG, Unternehmenskommunikation, Elektronische Medien, Germany. Project management, Aspirin digital marketing assets archive and Bayer quarterly company profile update

Senior Consultant, e-trend media consulting GmbH

05/1999 to 12/2000

Selected clients and projects:

Oniva NV, Venlo - Information Memorandum for Oniva group

WDSE Wirtschaftsdienste Soriano Eupen GmbH, Köln - Technical concept stock charting and stock management system

Loomes AG, Frankfurt a.M. - Project management for relaunch of eCommerce system for German domain hoster.

Oniva N.V., Venlo - Development of investment service product portfolio for various investors, Information Memorandum for clients in Germany and China.

Consultant, Telemedia, Gütersloh, Germany

01/1997 to 04/1999

Selected projects and responsibilities:

PMO for realization project of multi channel strategy for Bank24, Bonn, Germany

Evaluation of Digital Rights Management Systems and IT budgeting for BMG, New York.

Project management, Bertelsmann corporate management information intranet, Bertelsmann AG, Gütersloh

Technical due diligence and business evaluation of IT technologies for Bertelsmann Group: NetGravity, Firefly, Digital Rights Exchange.

Business modell and technical design of centralized "ad banner server" service for Gruner & Jahr AG & Co KG, Hamburg

Project manager, Bertelsmann MediaSystems GmbH, Germany

08/1995 to 12/1996

IT Consulting for Bertelsmann subsidiaries, selected projects and responsibilities:

Bertelsmann Bookclub, Industry and corporate communications

Development of eCommerce prototypes & business models: ICQ, web push services, online advertisement management

Project management and service design for private label online service, WAZ group, Essen $\,$

Technical due diligence of internet technologies for: Lycos, AOL, ICQ, BroadVision

Project management, Bertelsmann Media Systems Intranet, Bertelsmann Zentrale

Informationsverarbeitung GmbH, Gütersloh

Education

2019 – 2022	SAFe Scrum Master certification. Refresher online SQL training and Hong Kong University FinTech online training
1988 – 1992	University:Commercial information technology Master in Business Data Processing, concentrating on Databases, Marketing and Artificial Intelligence, European Business School, Schloß Reichartshausen. Degree: Diplom-Informatiker (Master in Computer Science) Thesis: Artificial Intelligence in Marketing
1/90 - 7/90	Regents Park College, London. Business Administration
8/90 – 1/91	San Diego State University (SDSU), San Diego. Robotics and Artificial Intelligence.

Secondary school ('Gymnasium'): German secondary school final exam (Abitur), main subjects: Mathematics, physics, art and geography.